Guide to the Mirra Ginsburg Papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
- Series IV: Background materials
  - Subseries IV.1: Singer Book projectBulgakov
    - About Bulgakov
      - Franklin, Simon; Furonskii, Mark; Lahr, John; Levin, Elena; Losev, V; Muchnic, Helen; Simonov, Konstantin; Vulis, A; Wright, A. Colin; About Bulgakov, 1967 - 1991 (Box 24, Folder 6)
    - Adaptations to Stage and Screen
      - Kadin, Daniel Scott Heart of the Dog - 4 typescripts with notes by MG, [1997] (Box 24, Folder 7)
      - Hemmerdinger, Lyn; Rifkin, Nancy Heart of the Dog stage adaptation - typescripts with ms notes (some by MG), 1983 (Box 24, Folder 8)
      - Klimov, Elem; Klimov, German Master I Margarita film synopsis, n.d. (Box 24, Folder 9)
      - Labedz, Chester S., Jr. Master I Margarita screenplay, 1997 (Box 24, Folder 10)
      - Liubimov, IUrii Master I Margarita play, 1985 (Box 24, Folder 11)
      - Tolkin, Stephen Master I Margarita - proposal for 6 part TV serial, [1982] (Box 24, Folder 12)
    - Clippings
      - Reviews comparing two Master and Margarita translations (Box 25, Folder 1 - 2)
      - Donovan, Gita; Otte, Charles; Serban, Andrei; Public Theater; Alchemy Theater Company; Project III Ensemble Theater Ads and reviews (Box 25, Folder 3)
  - Subseries IV.2: Russian Writers
    Original texts, research/biographic materials and reviews of Russian authors, translated by MG (except Bulgakov - see Bulgakov subseries). Arranged alphabetically by writer.
    - Aitmatov, Chingiz Aitmatov - background materials (Box 25, Folder 4)
    - Babel, Isaac Babel - texts of short stories and diary (Box 25, Folder 5)
    - Babel, Isaac Babel - reviews and ads for Sunset stage performances (Box 25, Folder 6)
    - Chukovskii, Kornei Chukovskii - background materials (Box 25, Folder 7)
    - Dostoyevsky, Fyodor; Fanger, Donald Dostoevsky - Notes From Underground introduction by Donald Fanger (Box 25, Folder 8)
    - Dostoyevsky, Fyodor Dostoevsky - background materials (Box 25, Folder 9)
    - Platonov, Andrei Platonov - texts of short stories (Box 25, Folder 10)
    - Platonov, Andrei (about); Bayley, John; Bocharov, S. G.; Karlinsky, Simon; Kern, Gary; May, Derwent; Mondich, M. Shimoniuk, M.; Turbin, Vladimir; Yakushev, Henryka; Yevtushenko, Yevgeny Aleksandrovich Platonov - background materials (Box 25, Folder 11)
    - Remizov, Aleksei Remizov - Russian texts of Skazki (Box 26, Folder 1)
    - Remizov, Aleksei Remizov - Russian texts of Martyn Zadeka, Nachalo slov; Besnovatye (Box 26, Folder 2)
    - Remizov, Aleksei Remizov Conference, Amherst College - Materials, Amherst, MA, May 1985 (Box 26, Folder 3)
    - Remizov, Aleksei (about); Bakhrakh, A; Shane, Alex M.; Shklovskii, Viktor Borisovich Remizov - background materials (Box 26, Folder 4)
    - Tynianov, IUrii (about); Belinkov, Arkadii; Tynianov - A Victory That Does Not Count (Box 26, Folder 5)
    - Zamiatin, Evgenii Ivanovich Zamiatin - Russian texts of Blokha (2 versions) (Box 26, Folder 6)
    - Zamiatin, Evgenii Ivanovich Zamiatin - Essays (Russian, French) (Box 26, Folder 7)
    - Zamiatin, Evgenii Ivanovich; Dikii, Aleksei; Yusim, Marat; Zamiatin - Blokha background materials (Box 26, Folder 8)
    - Zamiatin, Evgenii Ivanovich; Pervushin V.; Shane, Alex M.; Slonim, Mark; Zavalishin, Viacheslav; Zamiatin - background materials (Box 26, Folder 9)
    - Zamiatin, Evgenii Ivanovich V Zagorsk Na Bogomol'e; Zhitie Blokhi (Box 38, Folder 1)
      [Oversized]
    - Blok, Aleksandr; Mandel'shtam, Nadezhda; Evtushenko, Evgenii; Tsvetaeva, Marina; Zoshchenko, Mikhail; Printed Materials on Russian Writers (Box 38, Folder 2)
  - Subseries IV.3: Subject Files
    Contains materials on history, folklore, space exploration, Russia/Soviet Union, poetry, children's literature, publishing etc.
    - Ancient Egypt (Box 27, Folder 1)
    - Children's Literature (Box 27, Folder 2)
    - Folklore (Box 27, Folder 3)
    - Folklore - Regions of Russia (Box 27, Folder 4)
    - Folklore - Yiddish (Box 27, Folder 5)
    - Maps (Box 27, Folder 6)
    - Music - catalogs, flyers, 1946 - 1983 (Box 27, Folder 7)
    - Poetry Clippings and Notes, [1920s - 1980s] (Box 27, Folder 8)
    - Publishing (clippings) (Box 27, Folder 9)
    - Soviet Union - copyright (Box 27, Folder 10)
    - American Committee for Liberation, Inc; Institute for the Study of the USSR; Radio Liberty Soviet Union - Dispatches and Bulletins (Box 28, Folder 1)
    - Soviet Union/Russia - Miscellaneous (Box 28, Folder 2)
    - Soviet Union/Russia - Printed Materials (Box 38, Folder 3)
    - Neizvestnyi, Ernst Materials on Ernst Neizvestnyi (Box 38, Folder 4)
    - Winn, Marie "What Become of Childhood Innocence", New York Times Magazine, Jan. 25, 1981 (Box 38, Folder 5)
    - Space Exploration and Science - clippings, [1968 - 1994] (Box 28, Folder 3 - 4)
    - Translation - titles, vocabularies, bibliographies (Box 28, Folder 5)
- Series V: Biographic Material
  Personal documents relating to MG and her family
  - Bronia Ginsburg, [Bobruisk, Russia] - New York, NY, 1916 - 1974 (Box 28, Folder 6)
    [Includes Oct. 1916 letter to relatives from Bronia and Mirra (Marusia) Ginsburg.]
  - Bobruiskii Den' Newspaper, Bobruisk, Russia, Oct. 3, 1918 (Box 28, Folder 7)
    [The last issue published before the family left Bobruisk.]
  - Album, with notes from friends and sister Lily, [Libava, Latvia], 1925 (Box 28, Folder 8)
  - Baron Byng High School, Montreal, Canada, 1928 - 1930 (Box 28, Folder 9)
  - Contracts regarding Babel's Sunset (Zakat), New York,NY, 1947 - 1984 (Box 28, Folder 10)
  - CV's, biographies and autobiographies, New York,NY, [1959] - 1997 (Box 29, Folder 1)
  - Calendars, New York,NY, 1964 - 1965 (Box 29, Folder 2)
  - Financial Documents: account statement, New York,NY, Jan. 1987 (Box 29, Folder 3)
  - Readings for children, New York,NY, [1990s] (Box 29, Folder 4)
  - Unsigned Postcards (Box 29, Folder 5)
- Series VI: PEN
  Materials relating to MG activities in American PEN club and its committees. Includes agendas, munites, publications, and correspondence between committee members
  - Capouya, Emile; Christ, Ronald; Chute, B. J. (Joy); Congrat-Butlar, Stefan; Daniels, Guy; Frenaye, Frances; Halman, Talat; Kosinski, Jersy; Kussi, Peter; Lask, Thomas; Longland, Jean; Macrae, John; Plant, Richard; Purdy, Theodore; Rabassa, Gregory; Rosenthal, Raymond; Stillman, Beatrice; Wilkins, Sophie; Wolff, Helen. PEN Translation Committee - General, 1973 - 1992 (Box 29, Folder 6)
    [materials (include meeting agendas, minutes, printed, etc.)]
  - Chute, Joy; Macrae, John III; The Rights of The Translator, 1977 (Box 29, Folder 7)
  - Lesser, Rika Translator's Questionnaire, 1980 (Box 29, Folder 8)
  - Friedlander, Christine; Miller, Richard Translator's Model Contract, 1977 - 1981 (Box 29, Folder 9)
  - Lesser, Rika Handbook for Literary Translator, 1989 - 90 (Box 29, Folder 10)
  - Conferences on Translation, 1988 - 1991 (Box 29, Folder 11)
  - Congrat-Butlar, Stefan Materials for History of American Translation (Box 29, Folder 12)
    [Includes materials on MG and her CV]
  - Children Books Committee - Agendas and Meeting notes, 1991 - 1992 (Box 29, Folder 13)
- Series VII: Writings by Others
  Typescripts or unbound photocopies, often inscribed to Mirra Ginsburg by authors. Series does not include materials translated by MG (for original texts used for translation see Background Materials series). Alphabetical by author.
  - Aksenov, Vasilii Ozhog (Box 30, Folder 1 - 2)
  - Belinkov, Arkadii "Pis'mo kritika A. Belinkova", Posev, Aug. 1968 and misc. articles re: Belinkov (Box 30, Folder 3)
    [Inscribed to MG by author, New Haven, CT, Jan. 1969]
  - Belyi, Andrei; Trahan, Lisa (translator) Gogol (Box 30, Folder 4)
    [Inscribed to MG by L. Trahan]
  - Brodsky, Joseph; Tsvetaeva, Marina (about) Ob odnom stikhotvorenii (Box 30, Folder 5)
  - Chukovskaia, Lidiia Korneevna Predsmertie (Box 30, Folder 6)
  - Dubnova-Erlich, S. Obshchestvennyi oblik zhurnala Letopis', 1963 (Box 30, Folder 7)
    [Inscribed to MG by author]
  - Gorbanevskaia, Natal'ia Poems (Box 30, Folder 8)
  - Kristi, G. Stanislavskii I Meierkhol'd (Box 30, Folder 9)
  - Levin, Vadim Poems (Box 30, Folder 10)
    [Enclosures, removed from the book Glupaia Loshad']
  - McPhee, John; Dodge, Norton Townsend (about) The Ransom of Russian Art (Box 30, Folder 11)
  - Nitsberg, A. Glubina kartinnoi ploskosti (Box 30, Folder 12)
  - Rudich, Vasily Keepers of the Flame, 1991 (Box 30, Folder 13)
  - Rybakov, Anatolii Leto v Sosniakakh, 1964 (Box 30, Folder 14)
  - Sample, Norman Thoughts from Golgotha, 1992 (Box 30, Folder 15)
    [Letter to MG from author enclosed (copy - original removed to Correspondenc e series)]
  - Shmukler, IUliia Short stories (Box 30, Folder 16)
  - Siniavskii, A. (Andrei) [title unknown], Glava 3: Otets. (Box 30, Folder 17)
  - Solov'ev, Vladimir Ne plach' obo mne, 1982 (Box 30, Folder 18)
    [Inscribed to MG by author.]
  - Sosin, Gene Thirty-three Days in the Soviet Union (Box 30, Folder 19)
  - Tucker, Lisa; Tsvetaeva, Marina; Original poems and translations of Marina Tsvetaeva (Box 30, Folder 20)
  - Ventslova, Tomas Natsional'nye problemy v SSSR I sovremennaia sovetskaia literatura, 1987 (Box 30, Folder 21)
- Series VIII: Periodicals
  Alphabetical by title.
  - The Atlantic Vol. 251, No. 2. contains "Watching the Russians: the American effort to understand Soviet society", Feb. 1983 (Box 31, Folder 1)
  - Babel, Isaac; Riwkin, Ester; Riwkin, Joseph; Rosental, Raymond; Commentary Vol. 3, No. 2. Contains "The Fate of Isaac Babel" by Raymond Rosental and Babel's short story "The Awakening" translated by Ester and Joseph Riwkin, New York, NY, Feb. 1947 (Box 31, Folder 2)
  - Aleksandrov, A; Platonov, Andrei (about) Grani No. 77. Contains "O povesti Kotlovan Andreia Platonova" by A. Aleksandrov, Frankfurt am Main, Germany, 1970 (Box 31, Folder 3)
  - Levin, Elena; Pasternak, Boris Harvard Literary Bulletin Reprint from Vol. XV, No. 4. Contains "Nine Letters of Boris Pasternak" publication and foreword by Elena Levin, Cambridge, MA, Oct. 1967 (Box 31, Folder 4)
  - LEF No. 4., Moskva-Petrograd, 1924 (Box 31, Folder 5)
    [Very fragile. Encased.]
  - Babel, Isaac; Midstream Vol. 7, No. 4. Contains "Regards to Odessa" - MG's translation of Babel's short story Il'ia Isaakovich I Margarita Prokof'evna, New York, NY, Fall 1961 (Box 31, Folder 6)
  - The Modern Quarterly Vol. XI, No. 1. Contains: "Was the Bolshevik Revolution a Failure: a symposium"., New York, NY, Fall 1938 (Box 31, Folder 7)
  - Novyi Mir No. 10, Moskva, USSR, 1934 (Box 31, Folder 8)
    [Fragile, encased]
  - Aitmatov, Chingiz Novyi Mir No. 1. Contains "Belyi parokhod" by C. Aitmatov, Moskva, USSR, Jan. 1970 (Box 31, Folder 9)
  - Slonim, Mark; Tsvetaeva, Marina; Mandel'shtam, Osip (about) Oxford Slavonic Papers Vol. XI, extract. Contains "Istoriia odnogo posviashcheniia" by Marina Tsvetaeva, publication and introduction by Mark Slonim., 1964 (Box 31, Folder 10)
    [Inscribed to MG by Mark Slonim, Florence, Jun. 1964]
  - Nabokov, Vladimir; Pushkin, Aleksandr (about) Partisan Review Vol. XXII, No. 4. Contains: "On Translating Pushkin" by Vladimir Nabokov, New York, NY, Fall 1955 (Box 31, Folder 11)
  - Problems of Communism Special Issue: Nationalities and Nationalism in the USSR, Washington, DC, Sep. - Oct. 1967 (Box 32, Folder 1)
  - Twarog, Leon I. The Slavic and East European Journal Vol. XV, No. 1. Contains "The Case for the Slavic Literature Course in Translation" by L. Twarog, with marks by MG, Bloomington, IN, Spring 1957 (Box 32, Folder 2)
  - Collins, Christopher; Zamiatin, Evgenii (about) The Slavic and East European Journal Vol. X, No. 2, Contains "Zamjatin's We as Myth" by Cristopher Collins, Madison, WI, Summer 1966 (Box 32, Folder 3)
  - Sovremennye zapiski No. XXXVI, Paris, France, 1928 (Box 32, Folder 4)
  - Translation Vol. 1, No. 1. Contains "Approaches and Illustrations" by MG, New York, NY, Winter 1973 (Box 32, Folder 5)
  - Maddock, Mary; Zamiatin, Evgenii (about) Translation Review No. 17. Special issue Women in Translation. Conains book review for We, Dallas, TX, 1985 (Box 32, Folder 6)
  - Remizov, Aleksei TriQuarterly No. 27. Russian Literature and Culture in the West. Contains Ginsburg's translations of short stories by Aleksei Remizov., Evanston, IL, 1973, (2 copies 2 volumes) (Box 32, Folder 7 - 8)
- Series IX: Audiovisual
  - Subseries IX.1: Photos
    - Baker, Jonathan and Barchiesi, Franca (Steefel, Jeffrey); Brudne, Eva; Ginsburg, Bronia; Jones, Philip; Levine, Vadim (Greenberg, Victor); Litvinova, Tatiana; Ohly, Derek [and mother]; Shane, Lana and Vikki (Shane, Alex); [unidentified man] (Sadomskaia, Natalia); [Sterling], Max (Sterling, Nancy Rifkin) Correspondence Enclosures, 1966 - 1992 (Box 32, Folder 9)
    - Mirra Ginsburg, 1959 - 1998 (Box 32, Folder 10)
    - [Gaurberg], Roza and Sara; Geier, Sam; Ginsburg, Joseph; Ginsburg, Bronia; Likhter, Johanna; Wittenberg, Robert, [...], Grace and Nina; Family and friends, Russia; Latvia, 1910 - 1925 (Box 32, Folder 11)
    - Bulgakov, Mikhail; Tynianov, IUrii Russian Writers (Box 32, Folder 12)
    - Serban, Andrei Master and Margarita performance, 1978 (Box 32, Folder 13)
    - Petrograd, 1917 - illustrations for Zamiatin book (Box 32, Folder 14)
    - Singer, Isaac Bashevis; Congrat-Butlar, Stephan Singer photos, New York, NY, 1967 (Box 38, Folder 6)
      [See oversized]
  - Subseries IX.2: Audio
    - Singer, Isaac Bashevis; First and Second Singer Interviews, New York, NY, (120 min audiotape, ) (Box 38)
      [Stored in oversized box]
- Series X: Books
  - Subseries X.1: Anthologies
    By Title
    - Ginsburg, Mirra, ed. and tr. The Fatal Eggs, and Other Soviet Satire, New York: Macmillan Company, 1965 (Box 33)
      [Ms. notes by MG. Anthology includes: Romanov, Panteleimon; Kataev, Valentin; Bulgakov, Mikhail; Leonov, Leonid; Shishkov, V. IA; Lavrenev, Boris; Zamiatin, Evgenii; Zoshchenko, Mikhail; Ilf, Ilia/Petrov, Evgenii; Kol'tsov, Mikhail; Bermont, E.; Vasiliev, Ardadii; Sagin, L; Vorobyov, N; Laskin, Boris; Vesenin, E; Kazakov, IUrii. In CLIO.]
    - Mosty: literaturno-khudozhestvennyi i obshchestvenno-politicheskii al'manakh, Munchen: Izd-vo Tsentral'nogo Ob'edineniia Politicheskih Emigrantov iz SSSR., 1959 - 1962, (5 volumes ) (Box 33)
      [Vol. II signed by MG. Not in CLIO]
    - Glinka, Gleb, ed. Na Perevale: Sbornik proizvedenii pisatelei gruppy Pereval, N'iu-Iork: Izd-vo im. Chekhova, 1954 (Box 33)
      [Signed by MG. In CLIO.]
    - Nariadnyi burunduk: Altaiskie skazki, Moskva: Detskaia Literatura, 1967 (Box 33)
      [Fragile. With notes by MG. Not in CLIO]
    - Noonday 3. Includes Sunset (Zakat), translated by Mirra Ginsburg and Raymond Rosenthal., 1960, (2 copies ) (Box 33)
      [Enclosed letter from Kalfin, Robert (Nov. 28, n.y.) removed to Correspondence series. NOT in CLIO.]
    - Oleshek zolotye rozhki: skazki severnykh narodov., Leningrad: Detskaia Literatura, 1963 (Box 33)
      [Signed by MG. Not in CLIO]
    - Aleksandrova, B. A. Opal'nye povesti, N'iu-Iork: Izd-vo im. Chekhova, 1955 (Box 33)
      [Inscribed by MG to Kirill and Nina. In CLIO]
    - Shemiakin, I. D. (ed.) Polnyi Chtets-Deklamator, Vol. 1, St. Petersburg: Oros, n.d. (Box 33)
      [Fragile. Inscribed to Z. Geier, Bobruisk, Sep. 8, 1913. In CLIO. Fragile -waiting for encasing]
    - Pri solnyshke teplo, pri materi dobro (proverbs), Moskva: Detskaia Literatura, 1974 (Box 33)
      [Not in CLIO]
    - Voloshin, Aleksandr (ed.) Vechera pod zelenoi lampoi: literaturno-khudozhestvennyi sbornik., Berlin: Literatura, n.d. (Box 34)
      [Fragile - encased. In CLIO.]
    - Vozdushnye puti. Al'manakh, Nos. 2 - 5, N'iu Iork, R. N. Grinberg, 1961 - 1967, (4 volumes ) (Box 34)
      [In CLIO]
    - YCLA Song Book, New York: Young Circle League, n.d. [1930s] (Box 34)
  - Subseries X.2: Individual Authors
    Alphabetical by author
    - Akhmatova, Anna Andreevna Izbrannye stikhotvoreniia, N'iu-Iork: Izd-vo im. Chekhova, 1952 (Box 34)
    - Allen, William Sevastopol: On Photographs of War, Riverside, CA: Xenos Books, 1997 (Box 34)
    - Annenkov, IUrii. Teksts by: Zamiatin, Evgenii Ivanovich; Kuzmin, M. A. (Mikhail Alekseevich); Babenchikov, M. V. (Mikhail Vasil'evich) Portrety, Peterburg: Petropolis, 1922 (Box 34)
    - Averchenko, A. (Arkadii) Dvienadtsat' portretov znamenitykh liudei v Rossii., Parizh': Internationale Commerciale Revue, 1923 (Box 34)
    - BabelÂ´, I. (Isaak) Izbrannoe, Moskva: Khudozhestvennaia Literatura, 1966 (Box 34)
      [Enclosed letters removed to Yale University Press correspondence file. In CLIO]
    - Bryusov, Valery Yakovlevich Mig: Stikhi 1920-1921 gg., Berlin: Z. I. Grzhebin, 1922 (Box 34)
      [fragile. In CLIO.]
    - Bulgakov, Mikhail Afanas'evich; Ginsburg Mirra, tr. Flight, New York: Grove Press, 1969 (Box 34)
      [Ms. notes by MG. In CLIO]
    - Bulgakov, Mikhail Afanas'evich; Giulio Einaudi ed. Master i Margarita: neizdannye otryvki i episody, Torino: Einaudi; Bern: Scherz Verlag, 1967 (Box 34)
      [Ms. notes by MG. Enclosed notes and clippings removed to Master & Margarita Notes (Folder 14-12). Not in CLIO]
    - Bulgakov, Mikhail Afanas'evich Sbornik rasskazov, N'iu-Iork: Izd-vo im. Chekhova, 1952 (Box 34)
    - Bulgakov, Mikhail Afanas'evich (about); Proffer, Ellendea (ed.); A Pictorial biography of Mikhail Bulgakov / Mikhail Bulgakov--fotobiografiia, Ann Arbor, MI: Ardis, 1984 (Box 34)
    - Bunin, Ivan Alekseevich Petlistye ushi i drugie rasskazy., N'iu-Iork: Izd-vo im. Chekhova, 1954 (Box 35)
    - Chukovskii, Kornei Vysokoe iskusstvo: o printsipakh khudozhestvennogo perevoda, Moskva: Iskusstvo, 1964 (Box 35)
    - Chukovskii, Kornei Ot dvukh do piati, Moskva: Prosveshchenie, 1966 (Box 35)
      [Inscribed to MG by author, Peredelkino, Nov. 1966. This edition not in CLIO]
    - Chukovskii, Kornei Skazki, Moskva: Detskaia Literatura, 1984 (Box 35)
      [Enclosed letter from Elena Sokol (Feb. 15, 1985) removed to Correspondence series. Not in CLIO]
    - Chukovskii, Kornei Fedorino Gore, 1995 (Box 35)
      [Based on 1928 edition. Not in CLIO]
    - Chukovskii, Kornei Krokodil, Tver': Prometei, 1995 (Box 35)
      [Based on 1919 edition. Not in CLIO]
    - Chukovskii, Kornei Mukha-Tsokotukha, Moskva, 1995 (Box 35)
    - Fanger, Donald The Creation of Nikolai Gogol, Cambridge, MA: Belknap Press of Harvard University Press, 1979 (Box 35)
      [Inscribed to MG by author, Nov. 13, 1979. In CLIO]
    - Grebenshchikov, Georgii Volch'ia skazka, Southbury, Conn.: Alatas, n.d. (Box 35)
      [Fragile - encased. In CLIO (in BAR collection)]
    - Gumilev, N. (Nikolai) Zhemchuga, Berlin: Mysl', n.d. (Box 35)
      [Fragile - encased. CLIO has earlier edition: S.-Petersburg: Prometei, 1918]
    - Gumilev, N. (Nikolai) Sobranie sochinenii, Vashington, V. Kamkin, 1962 - 1966, (3 volumes ) (Box 35)
    - Gumilev, N. (Nikolai) (about); Kreid, Vadim, ed. Nikolai Gumilev v vospominaniiakh sovremennikov, Parizh; N'iu-Iork: Izd-vo Tret'ia volna, 1989 (Box 35)
    - Kaverin, V. (Veniamin); Novikov, Vladimir; Tynianov, IUrii Nikolaevich (about) Novoe zrenie, Moskva: Kniga, 1988 (Box 35)
    - Kaverin, V. (Veniamin), Epilog: memuary, Moskva: Moskovskii Rabochii, 1989 (Box 36)
      [Ms. notes by MG. Enclosed notes removed to Yale University Press correspondence file. In CLIO]
    - Kazak, Volfgang Entsiklopedicheskii slovar' russkoi literatury s 1917 goda., London: Overseas Publication Interchange, Ltd., 1988 (Box 36)
    - Khodasevich, V. F. (Vladislav Felitsianovich), Schaslivyi domik: vtoraia kniga stikhov, Berlin: Izd-vo Z.I. Grzhebina, 1922 (Box 36)
      [Fragile. In CLIO.]
    - Levin, Vadim Glupaia loshad', Novosibirsk, 1969 (Box 36)
      [Inscribed to MG by author, New York, Apr. 11, 1991. Not in CLIO]
    - Markish, David Shuty, ili khronika iz zhizni prokhozhikh liudei, 1689-1738, Tel-Aviv, 1983 (Box 36)
      [Inscribed to MG by author, New York, 5-11-1983 (not clear if May 11 or Nov. 5). In CLIO]
    - Pennant, Edmund Misapprehensions and Other Poems, Roanoke, VA: Lintel, 1984 (Box 36)
      [Inscribed to MG by author, May 30, 1987. Removed to Correspondence: letter from Pennant, Edmund, Jul. 21, 1987; from Zaslow, Shana, May 30, 1987. In CLIO.]
    - Remizov, Aleksei; Raevskaia-Kh'iuz, Ol'ga (ed.) Iveren', Berkeley: Berkeley Slavic Specialties, 1986 (Box 36)
    - Remizov, Aleksei (about); Sinany, Helene Alexis Remizov, Bibliographie, Paris: Institut D'etudes Slaves, 1978 (Box 36)
    - Romanov, Panteleimon Sobranie sochinenii, Vol. 4 - Detstvo., Moskva: Nikitinskie Subbotniki, 1926 (Box 36)
      [Fragile - encased. Not in CLIO]
    - Roziner, Feliks V domike starogo muzykanta, Moskva: Sovetskii kompositor, 1970 (Box 36)
      [Inscribed to MG by author, Oct. 1986. Not in CLIO]
    - Shane, Alex M; Zamiatin, Evgenii Ivanovich (about) The Life and Works of Evgenij Zamjatin. Berkeley: University of California Press, 1968 (Box 36)
      [Inscribed to MG by author, Dec. 6, 1968. Ms. notes by MG. In CLIO.]
    - Slobin, Greta Nachtailer, ed. Aleksej Remizov :Aapproaches to a Protean Writer. Papers presented at the Amherst Remizov Symposium held May 3-5, 1985, Columbus, Ohio: Slavica Publishers, [987], c1986 (Box 36)
    - Slobin, Greta Nachtailer Remizov's fictions, 1900-1921, DeKalb: Northern Illinois University Press, 1991 (Box 36)
      [Inscribed to MG by author, New York, 1992. In CLIO]
    - Shragin, Boris Iosifovich Protivostoianie dukha, London: Overseas Publication Interchange, Ltd., 1977 (Box 37)
      [Inscribed to MG by author, New York, Sep. 8, 1977. In CLIO]
    - Volokhonskii, Anri Roman-pokoinichek, N'iu-Iork: Gnozis, 1982 (Box 37)
    - Zamiatin, Evgenii Ivanovich Ogni sviatogo Dominika, Berlin: Slovo, 1922 (Box 37)
      [Fragile. CLIO has Ann Arbor, Mich., University Microfilms, 1973 (facsimile reprint of 1922 ed.)]
    - Zamiatin, Evgenii Ivanovich Na Kulichkakh, Berlin: Z. I. Grzhebin, 1923 (Box 37)
    - Zamiatin, Evgenii Ivanovich (Zamiatin, Eugene), Gregory Zilboorg, tr. We (My), translated by Gregory Zilboorg, New York: E. P. Dutton, c1952 (Box 37)
      [Reprint of 1924 edition. In CLIO]
    - Zamiatin, Evgenii Ivanovich (Zamyatin, Yevgeny); Ginsburg, Mirra, tr. A Soviet Heretic: Essays by Yevgeny Zamyatin, edited and translated by Mirra Ginsburg, Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1970 (Box 37)
      [Enclosures removed to Writings series, Soviet Heretic Notes folder (20 - 1). In CLIO]
    - Zamiatin, Evgenii Ivanovich (Zamyatin, Yevgeny); Ginsburg, Mirra, tr. We (My), translated by Mirra Ginsburg, New York: The Viking Press, 1972, (2 copies ) (Box 37)
      [Ms. notes by MG. Enclosures removed to Writings series, We Notes folder (20 - 4). In CLIO]
    - Zamiatin, Evgenii Ivanovich (Zamyatin, Yevgeny), Ginsburg, Mirra, tr. We (My), translated by Mirra Ginsburg, New York: Bantam Books, 1972, (2 copies ) (Box 37)
      [Enclosures removed to Writings series, We Notes folder (20 - 4). Not in CLIO]
    - Zoshchenko, Mikhail Uvazhaemye grazhdane: sbornik iumoristicheskiikh rasskazov., Paris: Ocharovannyi Strannik, 1927 (Box 37)
      [Fragile. CLIO has same title published by Moskva: Zemlia i fabrika, 1927. on Microfilm (1983).]
- Series XI: Oversized
  Oversized items from various series, cross-referenced in the corresponding series. Box also contains an audio cassette tape of Singer Interviews (paper materials on this project are in Writings - Singer series).
  - Zamiatin, Evgenii V Zagorsk na bogomol'e; Zhitie blokhi (Box 38, Folder 1)
  - Printed Materials on Russia and Soviet Union (Box 38, Folder 2)
  - Blok, Aleksandr; Mandel'shtam, Nadezhda; Evtushenko, Evgenii; Tsvetaeva, Marina; Zoshchenko, Mikhail; Printed Materials on Russian Writers (Box 38, Folder 3)
  - Neizvestnyi, Ernst Materials on Ernst Neizvestnyi (Box 38, Folder 4)